Charles Monroe Dickinson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Charles Monroe Dickinson Papers 1897-1928
MSS18432
Dickinson, Charles Monroe Dickinson, 1842-1924
1,000 items
4 containers
1.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, editor, and diplomat. Correspondence, writings, reminiscences, biographical material, clippings, passports, and photographs relating chiefly to Dickinson's activities as an American diplomatic representative in Bulgaria and Turkey, 1897-1908.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Dickinson, Charles Monroe, 1842-1924.; Dickinson, Charles Monroe, 1842-1924. Children, and other verses.; Merrill, Selah, 1837-1909.; Norton, Thomas H. (Thomas Herbert), 1851-1941.; Stone, Ellen Maria, 1846-1927.
Subjects
Consuls--Jerusalem.; Consuls--Turkey--İzmir.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Bulgaria.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Jerusalem.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Turkey.; Kidnapping--Macedonia.; Practice of law--United States.; Women missionaries--Macedonia.
Places
Bulgaria--Foreign relations--United States.; Turkey--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Bulgaria.; United States--Foreign relations--Turkey.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Editors.; Lawyers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Charles Monroe Dickinson, lawyer, editor, and diplomat, were deposited in the Library of Congress by his wife, Alice Bond Minard Dickinson, in 1933 and converted to a gift in 1957.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Charles Monroe Dickinson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1842, Nov. 15 Born, Lowville, N.Y.
1865 Admitted to New York bar
1878 1880 Editor and then owner and publisher of Binghamton Republic
1889 Published The Children and Other Verses. New York: Cassell & Co.
1897 1906 U.S. consul general, Constantinople, Turkey
1901 1907 Diplomatic agent to Bulgaria
1903 Negotiated release of American missionary kidnapped in Macedonia, Ellen Maria Stone
1924, July 3 Died, Binghamton, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Charles M. Dickinson (1842-1924) span the years 1897-1923, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1897-1908. The collection consists of correspondence, writings, reminiscences, biographical material, clippings, passports, and photographs relating chiefly to Dickinson's activities as an American diplomatic representative in Bulgaria and Turkey. Included is documentation pertaining to Ellen Maria Stone, a missionary abducted by brigands in Macedonia in 1901, and investigations of Thomas H. Norton and Selah Merrill, American consuls in Smyrna, Turkey, and Jerusalem, respectively. Also included is material relating to Dickinson's law practice in New York and reviews of his book, The Children, and Other Verses (1889).
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is organized by type of material
Container List
- Special correspondence (Box 1)
  - Laughton family, 1905-1906 (Box 1)
  - Merrill, Selah, 1906-1907 (Box 1)
  - Norton, Thomas H., 1905-1906 (Box 1)
  - Stone, Ellen Maria, case, 1901-1904, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Wheeler, Jeanne and Walter Frisbie, 1905-1908 (Box 1)
- General correspondence, 1897-1907, (11 folders) (Box 2)
- Subject file (Box 3)
  - Biographical material (Box 3)
  - Consular papers, 1895-1905 (Box 3)
  - Photograph and passport, 1923 (Box 3)
  - Reminiscences and writings (Box 3)
  - Clippings (Box 3)
- Letterbooks, 1901-1905 (Box 4)